The Epic Fall of the American Indian
Bury My Heart at Wounded Knee is a western, drama,
history film directed by Yves Simoneau.
Beginning just after the bloody Sioux victory over General Custer at Little Big Horn, the story is told through two unique perspectives: Charles Eastman, a young, white-educated Sioux doctor
held up as living proof of the alleged success of assimilation, and Sitting Bull the proud Lakota chief whose tribe won the American Indians’ last major victory at Little Big Horn.
Elaine Goodale, played by Anna Paquin.
Ohiyesa / Young Charles, played by Chevez Ezaneh.
Sitting Bull, played by August Schellenberg.
Uncle, played by Duane Howard.
Henry Dawes, played by Aidan Quinn.
General Sherman, played by Colm Feore.
Bury My Heart at Wounded Knee is a 2007 American Western historical drama television
film based on the 1970 non-fiction book of the same name by Dee Brown.
It is directed by Yves Simoneau and was produced by Wolf Films for HBO.
It stars Aidan Quinn, Adam Beach, August Schellenberg, Anna
Paquin, Colm Feore, and Gordon Tootoosis.
The film dramatizes the history of Native Americans in the American West in the 1860s and 1870s, focusing upon the transition from traditional ways of living to living on
reservations and their treatment during that period, through the lives of four main characters: Charles Eastman (Beach), Sitting Bull (Schellenberg), Henry L.
Dawes (Quinn), and Red Cloud (Tootoosis).
The title of the film and the book is taken from a line in the Stephen Vincent Benét
poem "American Names."
The film premiered on HBO on May 27, 2007.
It received positive reviews from critics, and won seven Primetime
Emmy Awards, including Outstanding Television Movie.
It was also nominated for three Golden Globe Awards: Best Limited or Anthology Series or Television Film, Best Actor –
Miniseries or Television Film for Beach, and Best Actress – Miniseries or Television Film for Paquin.
The film explores themes of war crimes, mass murder, native american,
native american attack, native american reservation.
The tone is emotional.